(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.1",
"generated_at": "2026-08-03T22:20:07.758233",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
ミラクル重大発表祭り
らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ
[Miracle Major Announcement Festival
Raden's New Costume Reveal 3D Live]
レーザービーム
Laser Beam
ストレート
Straight on
ドキドキする
heart's pounding
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is just like a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Stabbing my heart like a fizzing bubble
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
実る果実が水を弾いて
When ripe fruit gathers water droplets,
キラキラしてる光に似てる
it resembles sparkling lights.
グラウンドに立つキミの姿が
Your figure standing on the playground
まぶしくて少し照れちゃうけど
is so bright, it makes me a little shy.
ストレート
Straight on
まっすぐだね
it's so straightforward
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love must be a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Stabbing my heart like a fizzing bubble
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
ふたりを繋ぐ秘密の光
This secret light that connects us
あの日見つけた秘密の光
The secret light we found on that day
恋の瞬間 音は止まって
At the moment of love, sound stopped
時間はスローリーに
Time slowly...
恋の光線
...this laser of love.
ストレート
Straight on
ドキドキする
heart's pounding
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is just like a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Stabbing my heart like a fizzing bubble
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
ストレート
Straight on
まっすぐだね
it's so straightforward
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love must be a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Stabbing my heart like a fizzing bubble
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
いよーっ
Yoo-oh!
寄ってらっしゃい白
Come on in
見てらっしゃい
Take a look
始まりました！らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ！
It has begun! Raden's new outfit showcase 3D live!
今宵はまだまだこれから！
Tonight is just getting started!
皆さん、一緒に盛り上がっていきましょう！
Everyone, let's get hyped together!
尽きない好奇心
My endless curiosity
素晴らしきジャポニズムに触れて
Encountering wonderful Japonism
令和の風雲児
The revolutionary of the Reiwa era
皆々にお届け致しましょう
We shall deliver to one and all!
饒舌に情熱
Passionate with my eloquence
伝えたい愛に溢れている
Overflowing with the love I wish to convey
無知の知がきっと
Knowing that I know nothing will surely
素敵な始まりになるんだよ
Be the start of something wonderful
知って欲しい
I want you to know
たらふく味わって
Savoring it to the full
尊い人生
This precious life
紐解いた歴史に
In the unraveled history...
心惹かれていく
...my heart is drawn to it.
遥か遠く
To far away,
電波に乗って
riding the radio waves,
あなたまで
reaching you...
この想い
...these feelings,
純粋に伝えたい
I want to purely convey them.
新しい世界
A new world,
見せてあげる
I'll show it to you.
開口一番
First thing off,
やっちゃって
let's do it!
型破って
Breaking the mold...
はい、はい！
Yes, yes!
はい！
Yes!
はい、はい！
Yes, yes!
はい！
Yes!
浪漫を抱いた人生を　丸ごと賭けて傾きましょ
With a life full of romance, let's gamble it all and show off!
刹那に生きた足跡を　偉大な先人と共に
Leaving footprints of living in the moment, along with our great predecessors.
洒落た口切って手招く芸事の深淵
Starting off with a witty talk, beckoning into the abyss of performing arts.
相反する感情　愛憎超えていく感動
Conflicting emotions, moving beyond love and hate into pure inspiration.
遥か遠く世界超え宇宙まで　この想い果てしなく届けたい
Far away, beyond the world, into space, I want to deliver this endless feeling.
オリエンタル　オクシデンタル　どちらも愛しちゃって
Oriental, Occidental, loving them both.
掻き立てる衝動が加速する　創造の世界へと飛び込んで
The stirring impulse accelerates, plunging into the world of creation.
小噺に乗せて
Setting it to a short tale...
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Come one, come all! Take a look!
語り継いでいく　人世の想い
Handing down the thoughts and feelings of this fleeting world,
あなたの心に寄り添って
gently keeping close to your heart.
道楽主義で　小粋にいなせ
With a playboy attitude, smart and stylish,
そんな生き様　如何ですか？
how do you like this way of life?
遥か遠く電波に乗ってあなたまで　この想い純粋に伝えたい
Far away, riding the radio waves to reach you, I want to purely convey this feeling.
新しい世界見せてあげる　開口一番やっちゃって
I will show you a new world, starting things off with a bang!
破天荒に型破って打ち立てる　金字塔パンチライン時を超え
Breaking molds and doing things unheard of, establishing a monumental punchline that transcends time.
出囃子に乗せて　寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Setting it to the entrance theme music, come one, come all! Take a look!
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Come one, come all! Take a look!
はい、はい！
Yes, yes!
はい！
Yes!
はい、はい！
Yes, yes!
はい！ということで！
Alright! So with that...
ということで、始まりました！
With that, it has finally begun!
儒烏風亭らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ！
Juufuutei Raden's New Outfit Reveal 3D Live!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
はい、皆様、改めまして、こんばんは。
Yes, everyone, once again, good evening!
ホロライブデバイス、ReGLOSSの、美術司るミュージアムプリンセス担当、
In charge of managing art as the Museum Princess of Hololive DEV_IS's ReGLOSS...
儒烏風亭一門は前座見習い、
and a novice opening act of the Juufuutei school...
ちょっと待って。
Wait a second...
儒烏風亭らでんでございます！
I am Juufuutei Raden!
みんな来てくれて、ありがとうございます！
Thank you all so much for coming!
本日のハッシュタグは、「#らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ」で
Today's hashtag is #らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ (#RadenNewOutfitReveal3DLive).
いっぱいポストしてくれると、とても嬉しいです。よろしくお願いします。
I'd be so happy if you post a lot using it. Thank you!
「ちょっと待って、大丈夫？」って言われてます。大丈夫、大丈夫です。ありがとうございます。
People are asking, "Wait, are you okay?" I'm okay, I'm totally fine. Thank you so much!
はい。
Alright.
さあ、今回ね、らでん新衣装お披露目ライブ、ミラクル重大発表祭り！
Now, this New Outfit Reveal 3D Live is also a "Miracle Major Announcement Festival"!
タイトルにもある通り、何やら重大発表が
As the title suggests, there are some major announcements...
あるとか、ないとか。
or maybe not.
しかも、一つだけじゃないの！
And what's more, it's not just one!
ということで、今日はね、ぜひ最後までお楽しみください！
So please be sure to enjoy until the very end today!
さあ、そして皆様、気になってますよね？
And now, everyone, you're curious, aren't you?
この新衣装、いかがですか？
How do you like this new outfit?
ドゥンドゥクドゥンドゥクドゥンドゥン！
Dum-dum-dum-dum-dum!
どう？みんな、どうかな？
How is it? What do you think, everyone?
これが私、らでんの新衣装、ミュージアムプリンセス衣装です！どう？
This is my new outfit, the Museum Princess outfit! How is it?
どうかな？どうかな？
What do you think? What do you think?
どうかな、みんな？ちょっとね、今日ね、ラグがね、コメントのラグがあって、あれなんですけれども、
How is it, everyone? There's a bit of a delay on the comments today, but...
良い？良い？ありがとう！ありがとうございます！
Good? You like it? Thank you! Thank you so much!
かわいい！ありがとう！ありがとうございます！
Cute? Thank you! Thank you so much!
え、今回ですね、100万人記念ということで、さくらしおり先生にお仕立ていただきました！
This time, to celebrate reaching 1 million subscribers, Sakura Shiori-sensei designed it for me!
イェーイ！
Yay!
これもね、普段から応援してくださっている皆様のおかげです。
This is all thanks to everyone who always supports me.
本当にありがとう！ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much! Truly, thank you!
もちろんね、このライブのあと、アンコールライブっていうのがメンバー限定であるんですけれども、
Of course, after this live show, we'll have an encore live stream for members,
そこでまた、のんびりと、このお衣装について、詳しくね、見ていきたいと思いますので、
where we'll take a relaxed, closer look at this outfit,
気になるよって方はぜひ
so if you're interested, please...
...ぜひメンバーシップの方に加入していただければと思います。
...so I'd appreciate it if you could join our membership.
今日ね、お昼くらいにメンバーの方が使えるスタンプを追加されましたので、ぜひコメント欄で、よかったら使ってみてください。
Today around noon, we added stamps that members can use, so please try using them in the comments section.
もうみんな使いたくてたまらない、アロワナスタンプとかが追加されてるんで、ぜひ皆さんとね、コメント欄いっぱいアロワナを泳がせてください。よろしくお願いします！
An Arowana stamp that everyone is dying to use has been added, so please let lots of Arowanas swim in the comments. Thank you!
さあ、ということで、お衣装！改めて新衣装なんですが、今回衣装の他に、ちょっとね、1つ...
So, with that, the outfit! Once again, this is my new outfit, but in addition to the outfit this time, I actually have one...
とあるものを作りましたよ！まぁ、楽曲中にもね、出てきたんですけれども...
special thing I made! Well, it did appear during the song, but...
じゃんじゃかじゃんじゃんじゃん、あ、あ、逆、あ、じゃーん！
Ta-da-da-da-da! Oh, wait, backwards... Ta-da!
ステッキでございます！いいでしょ、これ。かっこいいでしょ。今回ね、特注でステッキ、作っちゃったー！
It's a cane! Isn't it great? It's cool, right? I had this cane custom-made this time!
しかも、これだけじゃないんですよ！
And that's not all!
見ててね。レーザービーム！
Watch closely. Laser beam!
ぶおーん！うわー！レーザービームだ！すごい！
Whoosh! Whoa! It's a laser beam! Amazing!
今回ね、あの、レーザービームを出せるようにしてもらいました。
This time, I had them make it so I can shoot a laser beam.
もう大丈夫です。疲れた。はぁ。
I'm good now. I'm tired. Phew.
いかん。もう今日はね、ライブまだまだこれからですので、体力は温存していかないと。
No, today's live performance is just getting started, so I have to conserve my energy.
でも今日は、自分の体力が、もう空っぽになるまで！全力でライブするから、みんな応援よろしくね！
But today, I'm going to perform with everything I've got until my stamina is completely empty! So please support me!
それでは、そろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思います。
Now, it's about time to move on to the next song.
さぁ次の曲は何なのか、重大発表とは何なのか、ワクワクしながら聞いてくださいね。
So, what is the next song, and what is the major announcement? Please listen with excitement.
そしてここからはゲストも登場します！ゲストパートは収録になりますので、悪しからず。
And from here, guests will also appear! Just so you know, the guest part is pre-recorded.
それでは、今夜はまだまだ始まったばかり。みんなで一緒に楽しみましょう！
So, tonight has only just begun. Let's all have fun together!
それでは、どうぞ！
Now, here you go!
そう高く 果てなく
So high, endlessly,
明日へと導くよ
it will guide us to tomorrow.
私だけの光放ちたい
I want to release my own unique light.
DIVE!
WOW...
自信なくしてたただ 心に鍵かけて
I had lost confidence, just locking up my heart,
響く自分の声に耳塞いでた
plugging my ears to my own echoing voice.
本当はいつだって わかっていたんだよ
Truth is, I always knew deep down
一番大切なもの ここにあること
that what's most precious is right here.
無限に広がる宇宙 迷わず進もう
Into the infinitely expanding sky, let's move forward without hesitation.
Go Fly! So High!
目を閉じて 言い聞かせてみただってもう
Even if I close my eyes and try to convince myself, it's no use.
身体中騒いでる 止まらない鼓動 強く熱く
My whole body is buzzing, this unstoppable heartbeat, strong and hot.
そう高く 果てなく
So high, endlessly,
抱きしめた未来が 奇跡になる
the future I embraced will become a miracle.
生まれた想いが 明日へと導くよ
The feelings that were born will guide us to tomorrow.
私だけの光 放ちたい DIVE!
I want to release my own unique light... DIVE!
WOW...
誰のものでもない 心に問いかけて
It belongs to no one else, questioning my own heart,
選んだ道の先へとまっすぐに
straight ahead toward the path I've chosen.
どんな時だって 見失わないよ
No matter when, I won't lose sight of it
一番大切な場所を 見つけたから
because I found the most precious place.
遠回りでもいい 胸張って進もう
Even if it's a detour, it's fine, let's march with our heads held high.
Louder! Sing Louder!
不器用かな でも傷ついたって構わないよ
Maybe I'm clumsy, but I don't care if I get hurt.
曇りない気持ちで 生きたい Pride 私らしく
I want to live with cloudless feelings... Pride, as myself.
両手を広げて 解き放った昨日が 翼になる
Spreading my arms wide, the yesterday I let go of becomes my wings.
重ねた出会いが
Our accumulated encounters...
この瞬間彩るよ
This moment is colored...
私だけの光 信じて
...believing in my own light,
DIVE!
空高く
High into the sky...
果てなく
...and boundlessly,
抱きしめた未来が 奇跡になる
the future we embraced becomes a miracle.
生まれた
The feelings...
思いが
...that were born...
明日へと導くよ
...will guide us to tomorrow.
私だけの光 放ちたい
I want to release my own light...
DIVE!
WOW WOW WOW WOW
JAPANの美術史♪ (アート！ アート！)
Japan's Art History! (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
Japan's Art History! (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
Japan's Art History! (Perfect for tests!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
O-Bo-E-Ma-SHOW!
さあ、3Dライブの途中ではございますが、ここで日本美術史の授業を始めたいと思います。
Now, even though we're in the middle of this 3D live, I'd like to start a Japanese art history lesson.
は〜い皆さんこんにちは！美術史を学ぶ時間です！
Hi everyone, hello! It's time to learn art history!
まずは縄文 弥生 古墳まで やってみよう！
First, let's explore from Jomon, Yayoi, to Kofun!
火焔型土器、遮光器土偶、縄文のビーナス！
Flame-style vessel, Shakoki-dogu, Jomon Venus!
銅鐸 銅戈 銅矛 銅剣 弥生土器！
Bronze bell, bronze halberd, bronze spear, bronze sword, Yayoi pottery!
埴輪も色々 踊る人々 挂甲武人 馬型埴輪
Various Haniwa: Dancing people, Keiko warrior, horse-shaped Haniwa!
古墳出土の鉄刀 鉄剣 七支刀に土師器 須恵器！
Iron knives/swords from Kofun, Shichishito, Haji & Sue pottery!
OK OK OK OK OKいい感じ！
OK, OK, OK, looking good!
次は飛鳥に奈良時代！
Next is Asuka and Nara periods!
さん！に！いち！ごー！
Three! Two! One! Go!
仏像いっぱい釈迦如来、菩薩と合わせて三尊像！
Many Buddhist statues: Shaka Nyorai and Bodhasittvas in Triad!
玉虫厨子、天寿国繍帳、金堂壁画、古墳壁画！
Tamamushi no Zushi, Tenjukoku Shucho, Kondo & Kofun murals!
東大寺には奈良の大仏、興福寺には阿修羅像！
Great Buddha of Nara in Todai-ji, Ashura statue in Kofuku-ji!
音と一緒に遊びましょう！螺鈿紫檀五絃琵琶！
Let's play along with the sound! Raden Shitan no Gogen Biwa!
未来のキミに届くように
Hoping it reaches the future you...
繋いでいこう この想い
...let's pass down these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, we'll be fine...
語り合う朝が来るまで
...until the morning we can talk arrives.
JAPANの美術史♪ (アート！ アート！)
Japan's Art History! (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
Japan's Art History! (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
Japan's Art History! (Perfect for tests!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
O-Bo-E-Ma-SHOW!
まだまだ色々ございます！がんばってついてきてくださいね！
There's still plenty more! Do your best to keep up!
平安 鎌倉 南北朝
Heian, Kamakura, Nanboku-cho...
参る！
Here I go!
曼荼羅、一木造り、寄木造り
Mandala, Ichiboku-zukuri, Yosegi-zukuri
鳥獣人物戯画に源氏物語
Choju-jinbutsu-giga and The Tale of Genji
平等院鳳凰堂阿弥陀如来坐像
The seated Amida Nyorai statue at Byodoin Hoo-do
模様がとってもかわいい片輪車螺鈿手箱！
The pattern is so cute, Katawaguruma Raden Tebako!
東大寺の南大門の金剛力士像！
The Kongorikishi statues at Todai-ji's Nandaimon!
阿弥陀二十五菩薩来迎図、山越阿弥陀図
Amida Nijugo Bosatsu Raigo-zu, Yamagoshi Amida-zu
蒙古襲来絵詞、空也上人像
Moko Shurai Ekotoba, Kuya Shonin statue
一遍上人絵伝、後三年合戦絵巻！
Ippen Shonin Eden, Gosannen Kassen Emaki!
YOYO! 半分くらい来たぜ多分！
YOYO! We're probably about halfway through!
まだまだいくぜありのまま、室町 安土桃山！
Still going as we are, Muromachi and Azuchi-Momoyama!
能面 翁に枯山水、天橋立図、呂洞賓図
Noh mask of Okina, Karesansui dry landscape, Ama-no-Hashidate-zu, Lu Dongbin-zu
狩野派の屏風！曜変天目茶碗！
Kano school folding screen! Yohen Tenmoku tea bowl!
洛中洛外図屏風、唐獅子図屏風、松鷹図
Rakuchu Rakugai-zu Byobu, Karajishi-zu Byobu, Matsu-Taka-zu
職人尽図、花下遊楽図、松林図、山水図、八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱！
Shokunin-zukushi-zu, Kaka Yuraku-zu, Shorin-zu, Sansui-zu, Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako!
本物だーーー！
It's the real deal!
未来のキミに届くように
Hoping it reaches the future you...
繋いでいこう この想い
...let's pass down these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, we'll be fine...
語り合う朝が来るまで
...until the morning we can talk arrives.
ここまでついてきてくれてありがとう！
Thank you for keeping up with me this far!
なんと今回特別に、バーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱さんに来ていただきました！ありがとうございます！
For this special occasion, we have the Virtual Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako-san here! Thank you!
あとちょっと、最後まで頑張ろう！
Just a little more, let's do our best until the end!
さあ最後、江戸時代から昭和まで、いきますよ！
Now the last stretch, from Edo to Showa period! Here we go!
さん！に！いち！なう！
Three! Two! One! Now!
舟橋蒔絵硯箱、風神雷神図屏風
Funabashi Makie Suzuribako, Fujin Raijin-zu Byobu
燕子花図屏風、見返り美人
Kakitsubata-zu Byobu, Mikaeri Bijin
好色一代男、奥の細道
Koshoku Ichidai Otoko, Oku no Hosomichi
奥の細道
The Narrow Road to the Deep North
富嶽三十六景、
Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji,
東海道中膝栗毛
Tokaidouchu Hizakurige
老猿、ゆあみ、坑夫
The Old Monkey, Bathing, Miner
墓守、伎芸天
The Grave Keeper, Gigeiten
竜虎図、黒き猫
Dragon and Tiger, Black Cat
鮭、海の幸
Salmon, Bounty of the Sea
渡頭の夕暮
Dusk at the Ferry
麗子微笑、紫禁城
Reiko Smiling, The Forbidden City
斑猫、五浦釣人
Tabby Cat, Izura Fisherman
太陽の塔
Tower of the Sun
吉原治良の円
Yoshihara Jiro's Circle
東山魁夷の道
Higashiyama Kaii's Path
未来のキミに届くように
Hoping it reaches you in the future,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's connect these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, it'll be fine.
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
Let's talk until morning comes,
未来まで
to the future!
最後行くよー！
Here's the last part!
JAPANの美術史♪
Japan's art history!
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
Let's memorize show!
ありがとうー！
Thank you!
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんらで〜ん！
To everyone watching the live stream, Konraden!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでの小話美術解説のお時間です！
We're in the middle of the live show, but now it's time for Raden's short art commentary!
なんと、今回ご紹介するのは、こちらで〜す、じゃじゃ〜ん！
And today, we will be introducing this, ta-da!
国宝、八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱、ということで
The National Treasure, "Eight-Bridge Iris Writing Box in Makie and Mother-of-Pearl," so...
今回、特別に東京国立博物館さんから3Dモデルをお借りしました！
this time, we specially borrowed a 3D model from the Tokyo National Museum!
いよっ、みんなにもよく見てもらいましょう、こちらでございます！
Alright, let's have everyone take a good look. Here it is!
こちらが、バーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱です！
This is the virtual Eight-Bridge Iris Writing Box!
螺鈿（らでん）ってなんか、どっかで聞いたことがありますね、なんかそんな名前のバーチャルYouTuberがいるような、いなかったような？
Raden... I feel like I've heard that somewhere before. Like, wasn't there a virtual YouTuber with a name like that?
こちらは、私のオリジナル曲、「JAPANの美術史♪お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！」にも登場する作品です！
This is a piece that also appears in my original song, "Japan's Art History: Let's Memorize Show!"
どうですか皆さん、この輝きとデザイン！
What do you think, everyone, of this brilliance and design?
大胆、かつ花びらの装飾の細かい部分も美しいこちらの作品、
Bold, yet beautifully decorated in the finest details of the petals, this piece...
作ったのは、尾形光琳という人です！
was created by Ogata Korin!
彼がこの硯箱を作ったのは江戸時代なんですが、どこかモダンな要素も感じることができます。
He made this writing box during the Edo period, but you can still feel some modern elements in it.
さて、工芸品を見るとき様々な見方がありますが、手助けになるのは「作品名」です！では、スライド行きます。
Now, there are various ways to view crafts, but what helps is the "title"! Let's move to the slide.
えー、この工芸品の名前を復習しましょう。八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱。漢字がたくさん入っていますが、一つ一つ紐解いていきます。
Now, let's review the name of this craft: Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako. It has many kanji, but let's break them down one by one.
まずは、「八橋（やつはし）」！
First is "Yatsuhashi" (Eight Bridges)!
日本美術史における工芸品は、物語の一場面や、和歌、歌ですね、がテーマになっていることが少なくありません。
Craftworks in Japanese art history are often themed around a scene from a story or a waka—a poem.
そして、この硯箱もその一つ！
And this writing box is one of them!
『伊勢物語』第九段、三河国八橋の場面が主題になっているんですよ。なので、これは「橋」ですね！
It's based on the Yatsuhashi scene in Mikawa Province from Section 9 of "The Tales of Ise." So, this represents the "bridges"!
八橋。この場面に出てくる八つの橋のこと。つまりは、何を描いたかを表しています。
Yatsuhashi. It refers to the eight bridges in that scene. In other words, it represents what was depicted.
では、何を描いたかが分かったら次に、どんな技法が使われたか。それを表すのが「蒔絵」、そして「螺鈿」です。
Now that we know what was depicted, next is what techniques were used. That is represented by "Makie" and "Raden."
「蒔絵」とは、簡単に言うと、金の粉を漆という接着剤を用いて貼り付けたもの。ここでいうと、
Simply put, "Makie" is gold powder sprinkled and fixed using lacquer as an adhesive. In this piece,
カキツバタの葉っぱの部分ですね！ピカピカ、ピンピンってなってるところです！
it's the leaves of the irises! Those shiny, pointy parts!
次に「螺鈿」とは、貝がらの光沢のある部分を薄くして貼り付けたもの。ここでいうと、
Next, "Raden" refers to thin pieces of iridescent shells inlaid onto the surface. In this piece,
カキツバタのお花の部分です！
it's the flowers of the irises!
この作品に使われているのはアワビ貝で、花びらを表現するためにあえて穴の開いた貝を使用しているのが分かります。
Abalone shells are used here, and you can see that they chose to use shells with natural holes to represent the petals.
そして最後に、そもそもこれは何か？それを表すのが「硯箱（すずりばこ）」です！
And finally, what is this object in the first place? That is represented by "Suzuribako" (writing box)!
えー、真ん中ご覧ください。こちら。
Please look at the center here.
えー、墨汁を作る硯入れが上の段にあり、さらにその段の下、
The upper tier contains the inkstone used to grind ink, and below that tier,
えー、下の段は、料紙、紙入れになっています！
the lower tier is designed to store writing paper!
さぁ、これで「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」の言葉の紐解きが完了しましたね！
Now, we have finished breaking down the name "Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako"!
カキツバタが咲く、川にかかる橋のダイナミックな魅力にも大注目のこの硯箱、
With dynamic focus on the bridges spanning the river where irises bloom, this writing box,
パカッと開けると、波が描かれています。
has wave patterns painted inside when you pop it open.
もうここまで聞いたら、何故そこに波の意匠を施したのか、皆さんならお分かりですね？上の段にある橋の下の...
Now that you've heard this much, I'm sure you all know why wave patterns were designed there, right? Below the bridges on the upper tier, there is...
波、ということですね。
Waves, is what it is.
実はですね、こちらの「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」
Actually, this "Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako"...
普段展示される際は、箱を閉じた状態なんですよ。
...is usually shown closed when exhibited.
つまり、中の様子をご覧いただけるのは、この配信ならではの貴重な機会です！
In other words, seeing inside is a precious opportunity only in this stream!
こちらがなんと、2026年5月26日から8月16日
This will actually be exhibited from May 26 to August 16, 2026,
本館2室にて展示されるとのことで
in Room 2 of the Main Building.
東京国立博物館さんでぜひ見てみていただければと思います！
I hope you'll check it out at the Tokyo National Museum!
この波のね、細かいところがすごく...
The fine details of these waves are so...
これ、筆でやってるんですからね。
This is actually done with a brush.
筆でこうやって...
With a brush, like this...
あ、お時間となってしまいました。
Ah, it's time already.
それでは皆さん、また次回お会いしましょう！
Well then, everyone, see you next time!
[特報 その①]
[Special Announcement Part 1]
[儒烏風亭らでん × 東京国立博物館]
[Juufutei Raden × Tokyo National Museum]
未来の君に届くように
So that it reaches the future you
繋いでいこう この思い
Let's connect these feelings
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there is love, it'll be alright
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
Let's talk to each other until morning comes
ということで、なんと！
And with that, oh my goodness!
私、儒烏風亭らでんと
I, Juufutei Raden, and...
東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定しました！
the Tokyo National Museum have a confirmed collaboration!
すごーい！
Amazing!
みんな、やったよー！
Everyone, I did it!
もうね、らでん、配信とかもういろんなところで
Raden has been saying in streams and various places
東博さんがね、ずっと大好きだって言ってたんですけれども
that she absolutely loves Tohaku...
今回ね、念願の東博らでんコラボでございます！
And now, it's my long-awaited Tohaku-Raden collaboration!
すごい！
Amazing!
あら、東博、さっき名前、聞きましたね？
Oh, "Tohaku"? We heard that name earlier, didn't we?
そうです！先日ね、10月から京都、
That's right! Recently, starting from October in Kyoto,
1月から東京にて開催予定の特別展
and January in Tokyo, the special exhibition
「源氏物語 王朝のかがやき」展の
"The Tale of Genji: Radiant Culture of the Japanese Imperial Court"...
音声ガイドのスペシャルトラックを務めさせていただくことが発表されましたが
It was announced that I will do the special track for the audio guide, but...
これね、これチラシね。
Here's the flyer.
なんと、この特別展「源氏物語」展の
Actually, for this "The Tale of Genji" exhibition,
東京会場となる、東京国立博物館さんとの...
its Tokyo venue, Tokyo National Museum...
ごめんなさい！
I'm sorry!
東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定いたしました！
Our collaboration with the Tokyo National Museum has been decided!
すごーい！
Amazing!
開催時期は、この「源氏物語」展と同じ
The collaboration will take place during the same period as "The Tale of Genji" exhibition,
2027年1月に実施予定となっております！
scheduled for January 2027!
なんで、こっちは「源氏物語」展・儒烏風亭らでんコラボ
So, this one is "The Tale of Genji" and Juufutei Raden collaboration,
そして、同じ1月に
and in the same January,
東京国立博物館・儒烏風亭らでんコラボがあると！
there's the Tokyo National Museum and Juufutei Raden collaboration!
もっと簡単に言うと、
To put it more simply,
来年の1月は東博のいろんなところに
next year in January, in various places of Tohaku,
らでんちゃんがね、出現しちゃいます！っていう感じです！
Raden-chan will pop up! That's how it is!
こちら、詳細はですね、また続報をお待ちいただければと思います！
As for the details, please wait for further updates!
すごいでしょう！すごい、すごい！
Isn't that amazing! So cool!
ということで、本日の重大発表1つ目は、
So, today's first major announcement...
東博・儒烏風亭らでんコラボでございました！
was the Tohaku and Juufutei Raden collaboration!
みんな、ありがとうー！
Thank you, everyone!
さあ、ライブも重大発表もまだまだ続きます。
Now, the live stream and major announcements will continue.
ちょっと待って。
Wait a second.
ちょっと疲れちゃった。
I'm a bit tired.
ということでね、
Anyway,
あの、東博、元々らでんが日本美術史に興味を持ったのって、
well, the reason I originally got interested in Japanese art history...
東博さんでの能面を見て、
...was when I saw Noh masks at Tohaku.
その時に「あぁ、なんて美しいんだ！」って思ったし、
At that time, I thought, "Ah, how beautiful!"
らでんって日本で生まれ育ったのに日本のこと本当に何も知らないんだなって思ったのがきっかけで、
I realized that even though I was born and raised in Japan, I really knew nothing about it.
そこから、なんやかんやあって日本美術史勉強したりして、
From there, after one thing or another, I studied Japanese art history,
なんやかんやあってホロライブに入って、
after one thing or another, I joined Hololive,
なんやかんやあって今こんな素敵な衣装をお披露目して、
after one thing or another, I'm revealing this wonderful outfit now,
なんやかんやあって、こんなありがたいコラボをさせていただけることになりました！
and after one thing or another, I got to do this incredibly grateful collaboration!
みんなのおかげだよ、ありがとうー！
It's all thanks to everyone, thank you!
もう人生本当に何が起こるか分かりません。
You really never know what will happen in life.
もう、とんでもない、何がどう未来へ繋がっていくのか、
I mean, it's crazy. You have no idea what or how it will connect to the future...
みたいのことももう分かりません。人生は奇妙な冒険みたいなものでございますな。
You just don't know. Life is like a bizarre adventure, isn't it?
さあ、ということでそろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思います。
All right, so I'd like to move on to the next song soon.
それでは聴いてください。
Please listen to...
「ココロパズルリズム」
"Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm".
はー...
Haa...
はーーー
Haaaa...
ココロのパズル
Heart's puzzle
ココロのリズム
Heart's rhythm
ココロのパズル
Heart's puzzle
ココロのリズム
Heart's rhythm
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
The future ahead, look, so many pieces
組み立てるのは キミしだい
It's up to you to assemble them
一つずつの 明日を生きる
Living tomorrow, one piece at a time,
ココロのパズルとリズム
the heart's puzzle and rhythm.
うまくは言えないけど
I can't put it well, but
不思議と安心して
strangely, I feel at ease,
いられる感覚って
feeling like I can be myself.
まるでパズルみたいだ
It's just like a puzzle.
もうずっと前から
From a long time ago,
僕らは予約席
our seats have been reserved.
さあ両手つないで
Now, hold both hands,
きっと一つになれる
we can surely become one.
完成が見えていても
Even if we can see the completion,
すんなりとはいかないね
it doesn't go smoothly, does it?
それぞれが夢のカケラだね
Each of us is a piece of a dream.
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
The future ahead, look, so many pieces
組み立てるのは キミしだい
It's up to you to assemble them
一つずつの 明日を生きる
Living tomorrow, one piece at a time,
空いた隙間を埋める
filling the empty gaps.
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
There are surely fun things too, but
それよりも大切なのは
more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
is when we're sad or when we're happy,
一緒に泣ける
to be able to cry together,
そんなココロのパズル
such a heart's puzzle.
すんなりとはいかないね
It doesn't go smoothly, does it?
キミと僕のパズルの行方も
The whereabouts of your and my puzzle too.
これからの love story ほらたくさんのピース
The love story ahead, look, so many pieces
間違えることもあるけど
There are times we make mistakes, but
胸に刻み 明日を生きる
engraving it in our hearts, we live tomorrow,
空いた隙間を埋める
filling the empty gaps.
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
There are surely fun things too, but
それよりも大切なのは
more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
is when we're sad or when we're happy,
一緒に泣ける
to be able to cry together,
そんなココロのリズム
such a heart's rhythm.
don't cry don't cry
walk hand in hand
ah ah 繋いで
ah ah, hold hands,
it's a nice day
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
The future ahead, look, so many pieces
組み立てるのは キミしだい
It's up to you to assemble them
一つずつの 明日を生きる
Living tomorrow, one piece at a time,
空いた隙間を埋める
filling the empty gaps.
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
There are surely fun things too, but
それよりも大切なのは
more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
is when we're sad or when we're happy,
一緒に泣ける
to be able to cry together,
そんなココロのパズル
such a heart's puzzle.
ココロのリズム
Heart's rhythm
はーーー
Haaaa...
ライブをご覧になってる皆様、こんばんは！
To everyone watching the live stream, good evening!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでの小話美術解説の時間です！
Although we're in the middle of the live, it's time for Raden's art trivia commentary!
今回ご紹介するのは…
What I'll be introducing this time is...
こちらで、じゃじゃーん！
this! Tada!
クロード・モネ『睡蓮の池』
Claude Monet, "The Water-Lily Pond"
今回なんと！ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております！本当にありがとうございます！
This time, we actually borrowed the image from The National Gallery in London! Thank you so very much!
皆さん、どうですか？
Everyone, what do you think?
私、モネの描く世界が大好きなんです。
I absolutely love the world that Monet paints.
モネと言えば、日本でもとても人気の高い画家ですが
Speaking of Monet, he is a highly popular painter in Japan as well,
彼の絵画の魅力はどのようなところにあるのでしょうか？
but what is the charm of his paintings?
今回は、彼の絵画に内在する魅力を言語化していきましょう！
This time, let's put the inherent charm of his paintings into words!
この作品は、1899年頃描かれました。
This piece was painted around 1899.
緑色の光が溢れる睡蓮の池には、大きな橋が架かり、橋の奥には柳が描かれています。
Over the water-lily pond filled with green light, a large bridge is built, and behind the bridge, willows are painted.
実はこの場所、モネの自宅に作った池なんです。
Actually, this place is a pond that Monet built at his own home.
フランスのジヴェルニーという町に家を購入した彼は、近隣の川から水を引いて、自分の理想とする庭を作りました。
He purchased a house in Giverny, France, drew water from a nearby river, and created his ideal garden.
アーチ状の大きな橋。これはいわゆる「太鼓橋」と呼ばれる橋と、柳。
A large arched bridge. This is a so-called "taiko-bashi" (drum bridge), and willows.
あれ、なんだか日本っぽさを感じませんか？
Wait, doesn't it feel somewhat Japanese-like?
それもそのはず。彼は日本の浮世絵に強く影響を受けた画家でした。
That makes sense. He was a painter heavily influenced by Japanese ukiyo-e.
彼の描く絵は光に溢れていて、目の前で風が吹いて、水面が揺れているようにも見えます。
The paintings he creates are overflowing with light, making it look as though wind is blowing right before your eyes and the water's surface is swaying.
じーっと見てると、水も、花も、木も、橋も、空気でさえも溶けていくようです。
Staring closely, the water, the flowers, the trees, the bridge, even the air seems to melt away.
見ていて落ち着く絵画だと思いませんか？
Don't you think it's a painting that feels peaceful to look at?
モネは絵を描くとき、色を混ぜて塗るのではなく、純粋な、何も混ざっていない色を「置く」ように塗りました。
When Monet painted, instead of mixing colors to apply them, he applied pure, unmixed colors as if "placing" them.
色は混ぜれば混ぜるほど、塗り重ねれば重ねるほど、暗くなっていきます。
The more you mix colors and the more layers you apply, the darker they become.
彼はこの課題を「色を置く」ことによって解決し、光に溢れた絵画の表現に成功したんです。
He solved this issue by "placing colors," successfully expressing a painting overflowing with light.
この絵画に近づいてみると、筆跡がしっかり残っています。
If you look closer at this painting, the brushstrokes remain clearly visible.
隣り合った絵の具一つ一つの相乗効果を計算し、絵の具の塊から温度感や湿度感を感じることができる風景へと変貌する表現は、モネが生涯かけて研究していたものです。
Calculating the synergetic effect of each neighboring paint, turning a clump of paint into a landscape where you can feel warmth and humidity, is the expression Monet researched throughout his life.
光を求めたモネが、陰影のない日本の浮世絵に強く惹かれたのも理解できますね。
It makes sense why Monet, in his pursuit of light, was strongly drawn to shadowless Japanese ukiyo-e.
彼の絵画の明るさは、画家としての研究の成果であり、情熱さえ感じられるそんな作品だと私は感じます。
The brightness of his paintings is the result of his research as an artist, and I feel it is a work where you can even sense his passion.
みんなはこの絵画、どう読んだかな？
How did everyone interpret this painting?
実はモネは「印象派」の画家と呼ばれるきっかけを作った人でもあるんですが、それはまた別のお話。
Actually, Monet was also the one who created the catalyst to be called an "Impressionist" painter, but that is a story for another time.
という感じでございまして、こちらはロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます！ぜひ行ってみてください！
And with that, this can be seen at The National Gallery in London! Please do go visit!
また次回！
See you next time!
I want to fight your brother
Let's kung-fu!
Every night I look to the skies and wonder what we did
Always a naive point of view
that breaks us in the end
If I could find the meaning of it all
I'd take the chance
Maybe in time we'll walk the mile
and change it if we can
It's now and always
How did we get this far, did we get this far na~
How did we get this far, did we get this far now
Always
We're making a brand new start, just a brand new start na~
We're making a brand new start, just a brand new start now
Always
Nothing will hold me down, never hold me down na~
Nothing will hold me down, never hold me down now
Always
Wave goodbye to me!
Around the world
新しいことに
To something brand new
Around the world
フミダスチカラで
With the power to take a step forward
Around the world
世界は変わるさ
The world will change
But don't run away 'cause if it's not ok!
But don't run away 'cause if it's not okay!
I'll change that world into something better, honey!
Let's kung-fu!
果てしなく広がる
Endlessly expanding
この大地を僕らは
this earth, we...
また歩き続けるさ
I will keep on walking...
全ての意味が分かるのならば
If we were to understand the meaning of everything,
この瞳で何を見つめるのだろう
what would we be looking at with these eyes?
IT'S NOW AND ALWAYS
HOW DID WE GET THIS FAR
ALWAYS
WE'RE MAKING A BRAND NEW START
NOTHING WILL HOLD ME DOWN
ALWAYS
WAVE GOOD BYE TO ME!
Wave goodbye to me!
AROUND THE WORLD 君だけのために
Around the world, just for you
AROUND THE WORLD 探し続けるよ
Around the world, I'll keep searching
AROUND THE WORLD 奇跡のかけらを
Around the world, for the pieces of a miracle
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
But don't run away, 'cause if it's not okay!
Yeah, and you know it's gonna be raining
And you know it's gonna be hard
As long as we trust each other, nothing's gonna break apart oh no! no!
If ya wanna be somebody, get up on ya feet and go
I know we're gonna meet each other somewhere around the globe
AROUND THE WORLD いつでも自分に
Around the world, those who always
AROUND THE WORLD 負けている人は
Around the world, lose to themselves
AROUND THE WORLD 何も掴めない
Around the world, can't grasp anything
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
But don't run away, 'cause if it's not okay!
I'LL CHANGE THAT WORLD INTO SOMETHING BETTER HONEY!
特報 その②
[Special News: Part 2]
儒烏風亭らでん × THE NATIONAL GALLERY LONDON
Juufutei Raden × The National Gallery London
儒烏風亭らでん ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリー コラボ決定!!
Juufutei Raden & London National Gallery Collaboration Confirmed!!
儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る世界の名画 A SHARED ART JOURNEY
World Masterpieces Reflected in Juufutei Raden's Eyes: A Shared Art Journey
5/20(水) 12:00よりグッズの予約販売が開始
Merchandise pre-orders start on May 20 (Wed) at 12:00 PM!
グッズラインナップ
[Goods List]
はい！
Yes!
ということでなんと、私 儒烏風亭らでんと...
And so, somehow, I, Juufutei Raden, and...
ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボが決定しました！
the collaboration with the London National Gallery has been confirmed!
ナショナル・ギャラリーさんといえば、モネ、ゴッホ、ターナー...
Speaking of the National Gallery, Monet, Van Gogh, Turner...
もうとにかくいろんな画家さんたちの...
Basically, so many painters'...
超有名な作品をいっぱい所蔵されているところなんですが
highly famous works are housed there.
なんとそんなナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ
And shockingly, this collaboration with the National Gallery...
「儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る世界の名画
is titled "World Masterpieces Reflected in Juufutei Raden's Eyes:
A SHARED ART JOURNEY」コラボ決定です！すごい！
A Shared Art Journey"! This is amazing!
さあこれね、とある3つの名画とコラボしてるんですが
Now, we are collaborating with three specific masterpieces.
みんな分かるかな？
Do you all know what they are?
3つね、3つあるんだけど
There are three of them.
では、左から行きましょうか
Well, let's start from the left.
左、ターナー 「雨、蒸気、速度―グレート・ウェスタン鉄道」
On the left is Turner's "Rain, Steam, and Speed - The Great Western Railway".
そして、真ん中。モネの「睡蓮の池」
Then, in the middle is Monet's "The Water-Lily Pond".
そして、一番右。これは皆さんお分かりでしょう。ゴッホの「ひまわり」
And on the far right, you all must know this one. Van Gogh's "Sunflowers".
そして今回、コラボ商品がございます。全8種あるんですよ。じゃあ1つずつね
And we have collaboration products this time! There are eight in total. Let's look at them one by one.
ちょっと紹介していきましょう。うーん、はい。
I'll introduce them. Yes...
えーまず、左上からいきましょうか。まずはフレグランスミストセットです。
First, let's start from the top left. This is the Fragrance Mist Set.
らでんが監修考案したフレグランスミスト。3点の名画が持つイメージを香りで表現しました。
Fragrance mists supervised and designed by Raden. Expressing the images of the three masterpieces in scents.
本商品はアルコールフリーのフレグランスミストなので、色んな場面に合わせて使用可能です。
Since this product is an alcohol-free fragrance mist, you can use it for various occasions.
じゃあ、隣いきましょうか。その隣、ローラーボールペン。
Let's move on to the next. Right next to it is the Rollerball Pen.
3つの名画のエッセンスと儒烏風亭らでんの家紋を見事に融合させたデザインでございます。
It's a design that beautifully fuses the essence of the three masterpieces with my family crest.
えーじゃあ次は、左下。えーカップ＆ソーサーセット。
Next up is the bottom left, the Cup & Saucer Set.
描き下ろしイラストからインスピレーションを得た、ボーンチャイナ製のカップ＆ソーサーセットでございます。
A bone china cup and saucer set inspired by the newly drawn illustrations.
ソーサーの中心には儒烏風亭らでんの名前も記載されています。
My name, Juufetei Raden, is also written on the center of the saucer.
最近らでんも紅茶飲めるようになったんで、お揃いにしましょうや！
Lately I've been able to drink black tea, so let's get matching cups!
えーそして、その隣がスカーフ。新たに描き下ろしたイラスト要素を組み合わせ...
And next to that is the Scarf. Combining elements of the newly drawn illustrations...
ファッション性と実用性を兼ね備えたデザインのスカーフでございます！
It is a scarf designed to be both fashionable and practical!
え、そしてじゃあ、そのお隣が、アクリルスタンド！本コラボならではの新衣装に身をまとうアクリルスタンドでございます！
And next to it is the acrylic stand! An acrylic stand featuring the new outfit exclusive to this collaboration!
えー、じゃあ、右上行きましょう！キャンバスアート！描き下ろしイラストを使用されるキャンバスアートでございます！
Let's move to the top right! Canvas art! It features our newly drawn illustration!
その下はトートバッグ！表面には本コラボのために描き下ろされたイラスト、裏面には３点の絵画のディティールをあしらったデザインの両面仕様となっています！
Below that is the tote bag! It's double-sided, with the newly drawn illustration on the front and details of three paintings on the back!
そして最後、ランダムクリアカードになります！全６種のランダムクリアカードで、一部のカードには箔押しデジタルサインと特別なメッセージが入っていますよ！
And finally, the random clear cards! Six types in total, and some contain a foil-stamped digital signature and a special message!
グッズいいでしょう？どれも素敵でしょう？
Great merchandise, right? Aren't they all wonderful?
そして、さらに！グッズだけではございません！ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボで、音声ガイドも収録させていただきました！すごい！
And what's more, it's not just merchandise! We also recorded an audio guide in collaboration with the London National Gallery! Awesome!
しかもこちらね、なんと、らでんの公式チャンネルにてアップする予定でございますが、詳細は後日公開予定となりますので、続報をお待ちください！
What's more, we plan to upload this on Raden's official channel, with details coming soon, so please stay tuned for more information!
と、グッズとガイドと盛りだくさんなんですが、みんなロンドンのナショナルギャラリー、どんなとこか…ごめんなさい、ふふ。ちょっと待って。
We have plenty of goods and the guide, but do you know what the National Gallery... sorry, haha. Hold on.
ロンドンのナショナルギャラリー、どんなとこか気になりませんか？
Aren't you curious about what the National Gallery in London is like?
ロンドンの街並み、見てみたくないですか？
Don't you want to see the streets of London?
ということで、なんと、実は！ReGLOSSメンバーで、ロンドンロケに行ってきましたー！
So, actually, the members of ReGLOSS went on a location shoot in London!
そのロケの様子は、ReGLOSSチャンネルなどで後日公開予定となっておりますので、こちらもぜひお楽しみに！
The footage from the shoot will be uploaded on the ReGLOSS channel at a later date, so please look forward to it!
ということで、重大告知その２は、重風亭らでんとロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボでございました！ありがとう！
So, Major Announcement #2 was my collaboration with the National Gallery in London! Thank you!
そして今、スタッフさんの方から、どうやら今、Xで、これXですか？Xでトレンド2位だそうです！すごい！みんなありがとう！
And just now, the staff told me we are currently trending #2 on X! Is it X? That's amazing! Thank you, everyone!
大丈夫かな？トレンド2位に入った理由が「らでんちゃんの体力が心配です」でめっちゃ入ってたらどうしようかな。
I hope it's okay. What if we trended because everyone was tweeting, 'I'm worried about Raden's stamina'?
でも今日は！今日はもう体力がもうすっからかんになって、次の日動けなくなるまで頑張るってらでんは決めたんです！だから今日は、みんなもね、いっぱい、いっぱい楽しんでほしいです！どうですか、皆さん、ついてこれてますかー？
But today, Raden decided to push myself until my stamina is completely drained and I can't move tomorrow! So I want everyone to enjoy yourselves to the fullest today! Are you keeping up, everyone?
あ、待ってくださいね。重大発表、まだあるんです！まだあるんです！これで終わりじゃないんですよ！しかも、ライブもまだまだ続きますので、皆さんチャンネルはそのままでございますよ！
Ah, wait a moment. There are still more major announcements! This isn't the end! And the concert will continue, so please stay tuned!
では、次の曲に行きたいと思います！それでは、どうぞ！
Now, let's move on to the next song! Here it is, enjoy!
水面に映った藍
Reflected indigo on the water's surface
眩しく揺れる
shining and swaying in brilliance
手探りで探してた
Groping, I searched
足りない私
for the part of me that was missing
ゆっくりと動き出した
Slowly, it began to move
何万年も前から
as if, from tens of thousands of years ago,
この時を約束されていた
this moment had been promised,
みたいにほら
see, just like that
風は歌い
The wind sings
雨は語り
the rain speaks
たどり着くよ 光のすみかへ
I'll reach it, the dwelling of light
幾重にも重なってる
Layer upon layer, overlapping
この地球(ほし)の偶然
the coincidences of this planet
影の向こう
Beyond the shadow,
真実の色
the true colors,
見つけ出すよ
I will find
光のすみかを
the dwelling of light
一つでも欠けていたら
If even one thing had been missing,
きっと出会えてなかったね
we surely would never have met
飛べぬまま見上げてた
Unable to fly, I gazed upward
透明な空から
from the clear sky
透明な空から...
From the transparent sky...
真っすぐに差し込んだ
shining straight down,
優しい朝日
is the gentle morning sun.
過ぎた季節が歪に
The past seasons, distortedly,
削った今という瞬き
shaved away this blink of an eye called "now".
どこにも同じものはないの
There is nothing identical anywhere.
ほら 生きてる証
Look, it's the proof that we're alive.
風は歌い
The wind sings,
雨は語り
the rain speaks,
たどり着くよ 光のすみかへ
we will arrive at the dwelling of light.
幾重にも重なってる
Overlapping in countless layers,
この地球の偶然
are the coincidences of this planet.
影の向こう 真実の色
Beyond the shadows, the color of truth,
見つけ出すよ 光のすみかを
I will find it, the dwelling of light.
一つでも欠けていたら
If even one piece had been missing,
きっと 出会えてなかったね
we surely would never have met.
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは！
To everyone watching the live stream, good evening!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、
らでんの小噺美術解説のお時間です！
We are in the middle of the show, but now it's time
for Raden's Quick Art Lecture!
今回ご紹介するのは、こちらでん！じゃん！
The one we are introducing this time is this! Ta-da!
フィンセント・ファン・ゴッホ「ひまわり」
Vincent van Gogh's "Sunflowers".
今回ナショナル・ギャラリーさんより、
画像をお借りしております。ありがとうございます！
For this, we have borrowed the image
from The National Gallery. Thank you very much!
ゴッホといえば「ひまわり」というイメージを
持っている方も、少なくないのではないでしょうか？
Many of you probably associate Van Gogh
with "Sunflowers," right?
それもそのはず、実は、ゴッホの描いた
「ひまわり」は1つだけじゃないんです。
And for good reason! In fact, Van Gogh
didn't paint just one "Sunflowers".
この世界に、失われたものも含めて、
7つの「ひまわり」があったんですよ。
In this world, including the ones that were lost,
there were seven "Sunflowers" paintings!
さて、では実際に、作品をじっくり見てみましょう！
Now, let's actually take a close look at the artwork!
みんなはどんな感想を持ったかな？
I wonder what impressions all of you have?
あらためて見てみると、いろんなことが見えてきます。
Looking at it again, we can see many different details.
よく見ると、ひまわりの花の向きはバラバラで、
花びらも不揃いですね。
If you look closely, the sunflowers face in various
directions, and their petals are uneven.
しかし、あたたかみのある黄色が画面全体を包み込むことで、
どこか生命力が溢れているようにも見えませんか？
However, with the warm yellow enveloping the canvas,
doesn't it somehow look full of vitality?
ここからは、ゴッホと黄色、そしてゴッホとひまわりに
ついて紐解いていきましょう。
From here, let's unpack the relationship between
Van Gogh and yellow, and Van Gogh and sunflowers.
「太陽は淡い硫黄の輝きを伝達するのだ」という言葉を
残しているゴッホは、太陽の光を黄色で表現しました。
"The sun conveys a pale sulfur glow," Van Gogh once said,
representing sunlight with yellow.
そして黄色は、ゴッホにとって
生命力の象徴でもあります。
Yellow was also a symbol of vitality for Van Gogh.
この絵を描いたとき、彼はフランス南部の
アルルという街で、
When he painted this, he was in the city of Arles
in the south of France,
心機一転、画家として仲間と頑張っていこうと
意気込んでいました。
starting afresh with a determination to work hard
as an artist alongside his peers.
そんな気持ちを黄色に託したのかもしれません。
Perhaps he projected those feelings into the color yellow.
一方で、この絵のモチーフになっている「ひまわり」
について見てみましょう。
On the other hand, let's look at the sunflowers,
which are the motif of this painting.
ひまわりは、太陽に向かって咲きます。
Sunflowers bloom facing the sun.
太陽は、西洋美術史において「神」を象徴します。
In Western art history, the sun symbolizes "God".
それに向かって咲くひまわりは、崇拝、従順、
忠誠、そして信仰心や愛を象徴します。
Sunflowers blooming toward it symbolize devotion,
obedience, loyalty, and also faith and love.
ここでさらに遠回りして、
彼の過去について知っていきましょう。
Here, let's take a slight detour
to learn more about his past.
先ほど、ゴッホがアルルでの生活を始めたとき、
私は「心機一転」という表現をしました。
Earlier, I used the expression "starting afresh"
when Van Gogh began his life in Arles.
実は彼、もともとは牧師さんになりたかったんです。
Actually, he originally wanted to become a pastor.
彼は頑張って勉強や奉仕活動に注力しますが、
うまくいきませんでした。
He studied hard and devoted himself to missionary work,
but it didn't go well.
画家への転身は、牧師さんへの道を
断たれた後のことだったんですね。
His transition to becoming a painter happened
after his path to the priesthood was cut off.
そんな彼が描く、信仰の象徴である「ひまわり」。
And so, he painted the "Sunflowers"
as a symbol of faith.
皆様はどう読み解きますか？
How do you interpret this?
未来への希望の光？それとも、自分への失望？
A light of hope for the future?
Or a disappointment in himself?
ゴッホの見た「光のすみか」は
「ひまわり」にあったのかもしれませんね。
The "dwelling of light" Van Gogh saw
might have been in the sunflowers themselves.
という感じでございまして、こちらもロンドンの
ナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます！
And that's the story! You can also view this masterpiece
at The National Gallery in London!
ぜひぜひ、行ってみてください！
Please, definitely go and check it out!
あ、また次回！
Ah, see you next time!
はい！ということで、早いもので次が最後の曲でございますが、
Yes! So, time flies, and the next one will be the final song, but...
なんと！儒烏風亭らでん、
...amazingly, Juufutei Raden...
新曲をリリースします！イェーイ！
...is releasing a new song! Yay!
特報、配信リリース！
Breaking news: Digital release!
タイトルは「ミラクルパレット」！
The title is "Miracle Palette"!
はい、えーこちらですね。えー、楽曲リリースなんですが、5月18日の0時0分...
Yes, here it is. The song will be released on May 18th at midnight...
ま、なので、今日の日付が変わったタイミングでリリースされます。
So, basically, it will release as soon as the date changes today.
5月18日といえば、そう皆さん大正解！国際博物館の日でございます！
Speaking of May 18th, yes, you got it! It's International Museum Day!
そんなね、特別な日にリリース！
Releasing on such a special day!
そして、この配信が終わってすぐ！
And right after this stream ends...
MVですね！なんとミュージックビデオが公開されます！
...the MV! The music video will be released!
儒烏風亭らでん初のダンスてんこ盛り3D MVとなっております！
It's Juufutei Raden's very first dance-packed 3D MV!
そしてこちら、楽曲コンセプトはジャズっぽいね感じになっております！
And the song concept has a very jazzy feel!
ということで、
And so,
今からライブバージョン、ミラクルパレットを披露したいと思います！
I'd like to perform the live version of "Miracle Palette" right now!
ダンサーさんカモン！
Dancers, come on!
よろしくお願いします！お願いします！
Pleased to work with you! Thank you!
はい！ありがとう。ペンライト振ってくれてありがとうございます！
Yes! Thank you. Thank you for waving your penlights!
では、聴いてください。ミラクルパレット。
Now, please listen. "Miracle Palette".
暗がりステージに立つ 雨傘を携え
Standing on the dark stage, carrying an umbrella
朧に霞む構図 印象 儚く
The dimly hazy composition creates a fleeting impression
始めましょ 雨粒ドローイング
Let's begin our raindrop drawing
キャンヴァスはこの空、この世界
The canvas is this sky, this world
Hop Hop 飛び回る
Hop Hop, jumping around
Tap Tap 打ち鳴らす
Tap Tap, stamping along
Dance Dance ぐるぐる
Dance Dance, spinning around
いざ ショータイム
Now, it's showtime!
(Ladies and Gentleman, Welcome to our magical show !)
(Ladies and gentlemen, welcome to our magical show!)
スポットライトを浴びて
Basking in the spotlight,
輝きを放つ
radiating brilliance
エンタシスよりプリズム
More than entasis, it's a prism
分光をスタンバイ
Preparing spectral dispersion
(この鈍色の空に 七色の橋を架けて見せましょう)
(Let me bridge this dull gray sky with a rainbow of seven colors)
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Now, look closely and behold!
目に映るもの、今を彩るから
Everything in sight will color the present moment
大きな絵筆で描き出す
Drawing with a giant paintbrush,
大胆なパースの中 嗚呼
within a bold perspective, ah!
びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
This drenched stage is a miraculous palette!
マスかレイドな第二部の開演
The masquerade's second act begins
Shall we dance?
モノトーンから極彩色に
From monochrome to vibrant rich colors
アシンメトリーなグラデーションで
with asymmetrical gradations,
夢中になってほしいの
I want you to be completely captivated,
雨雲にマーブリング
marbling across the rainclouds
目を奪われたその隙
The moment your eyes are stolen,
イリュージョンをスタンバイ
preparing the illusion
(ところで皆さん、なくし物はございませんか？)
(By the way, everyone, have you lost anything?)
どなた様もおいでませ！
Welcome, one and all!
あの手この手で魅了していくから
Because I will charm you with every trick up my sleeve
一足お先にまんまと
Boldly, one step ahead,
盗みだすわ あなたの心を
I'll steal away your heart
光を放ち出す
Radiating light,
きらめきのパレット
a sparkling palette!
(さてさて！いよいよ大詰め、クライマックスに向けて盛り上がってまいりましょう！)
(Now, now! We're finally entering the final stretch, let's get hyped for the climax!)
Listen!
OK, 5・4・3・2・1・Go on the Show!
OK, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, Go on the Show!
最大級のキャンヴァスに描き出す
Drawing on the grandest canvas of all
誰も見たことのない景色
a landscape nobody has ever seen before!
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Now, look closely and behold!
次元の壁を超えて閃くから
For it flashes past the boundaries of dimensions!
大きな絵筆で描き出す
Drawing with a giant paintbrush...
大、大胆なパースの中
Inside the daring perspective...
さあ みんなで大団円
Now, let's welcome a grand finale together!
迎えに行こう
Let's go welcome it!
嗚呼
Ah...
びしょ濡れの舞台は
The soaking wet stage...
ミラクルなパレット
is a miraculous palette!
Oh...
特報
[Special Announcement]
特報 その③
[Special Announcement Part 3]
ピクセルミュージアム 新情報
[Pixel Museum: New Information]
箱根探訪編 DLC
[Hakone Visit Edition DLC]
さあ とくとご覧あれ
Now, feast your eyes!
目に映るもの 今を彩るから
For I will color the things reflected in your eyes!
ポン！
Bam!
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内！ ピクセルミュージアム
Guided by Juufuutei Raden! Pixel Museum
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ「箱根探訪編」配信決定！
Additional DLC "Hakone Visit Edition" decided!
イベント展示のご案内
Information on event exhibitions
今回のテーマは、箱根！
This time, the theme is... Hakone!
らでん館長の大好きな箱根にまつわる作品をご用意しました。
We have prepared works related to Hakone, which Director Raden loves.
館内もイベント仕様で、箱根の魅力がたっぷりと詰まっています。
The museum also has an event layout, packed with the charms of Hakone!
もちろん、解説はフルボイスでお届けしますよ！
Of course, the audio guides will be in full voice!
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内！ ピクセルミュージアム 追加ダウンロードコンテンツ
Guided by Juufuutei Raden! Pixel Museum, additional downloadable content...
「箱根探訪編」、2026年12月配信予定！
..."Hakone Visit Edition," scheduled for release in December 2026!
ちょっと待つたけね！
Please wait a little bit!
な、な、なんと！
W-W-What?!
昨年6月5日の発売から1年を待たずに！
In less than a year since its release on June 5th last year...
「儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム」の追加ダウンロードコンテンツ、「箱根探訪編」の配信が...
...the release of "Juufuutei Raden Guides You: Pixel Museum" additional DLC, "Hakone Visit Edition"...
決定いたしましたー！やったー！
...has been officially decided! Yay!
みんながね、いっぱいダウンロードしてくれて、みんながたくさん遊んでくれたおかげです！
This is all thanks to everyone downloading it and playing it so much!
本当にありがとうございます！
Thank you so very much!
今回の舞台は、皆様お馴染みの「箱根」でございます！
This time, the stage is the familiar "Hakone"!
えー、前作に引き続き、「箱根ガラスの森美術館」様に加え、
Following the previous installment, in addition to the "Hakone Glass no Mori Museum"...
今回はなんと！
...this time, believe it or not...
「ポーラ美術館」様と
...the "Pola Museum of Art"...
「小田急箱根」様にもご協力いただけることとなりました！拍手！
...and "Odakyu Hakone" are also cooperating with us! Claps!
えー、館長のプライベートルームもイベント仕様にアップデート！
The Director's private room is also updated with event specs!
箱根の魅力マシマシでお届けいたしますよ！いいでしょう！
We will bring you the charm of Hakone in full force! Great, right?
そんな追加ダウンロードコンテンツ「箱根探訪編」は、
That additional DLC, "Hakone Visit Edition,"...
2026年12月に配信予定！
...is scheduled to be released in December 2026!
そうですね、来週5月23日、24日に、
And next week, on May 23rd and 24th,
京都にて開催されます
held in Kyoto,
「BitSummit Drift」に「らでピク」も登場！
"Rade-Pix" will make an appearance at "BitSummit Drift"!
大好評発売中の「らでピク」の試遊や、
You can play the demo of "Rade-Pix," which is currently on sale,
「箱根探訪編」のキービジュアルポストカードの配布もあるみたいですよ！
and it seems they will also distribute key visual postcards of "Hakone Visit Edition"!
詳しい情報は公式ホームページと、ジュピターさんの公式Xを要チェックです！
Be sure to check the official homepage and Jupiter's official X for details!
まだまだ嬉しい情報もあるかも？
There might be even more exciting news in store!
それではリリースまでお楽しみに！
So, please look forward to the release!
はい！えー、そして！そして！
Yes! And! And!
皆さんお待ちかね、儒烏風亭らでん100万人記念グッズが発売されます！
What you've all been waiting for: Juufuutei Raden's 1 Million Subscribers Commemorative Goods will be on sale!
ごめんね、今日本当に何か発表が多くて
Sorry, there are really so many announcements today...
えー、早速詳細見ていきましょう、一つ目はこちら、デン！
Let's check out the details right away. First, this one, bam!
「新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック」
"Live in New Outfit! Acrylic Block"
いや、めっちゃ疲れてる、らでんが写っちゃった
Ah, I look so exhausted in that shot...
新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック
Live in New Outfit! Acrylic Block.
ライブステージで楽しそうに歌う新衣装のらでん
This features Raden singing happily on the live stage in her new outfit,
もりくらえん先生の描き下ろしでございます！
illustrated by Morikura En-sensei!
こちら、アクリルブロックの表裏に印刷されておりまして、めっちゃね奥行きが感じられるものとなっておるんですよ。
This is printed on both the front and back of the acrylic block, giving it a real sense of depth!
続いてはこちら、デン！
Next up, this one, bam!
「らでんの衣装いろいろ3連結アクリルキーホルダー」
"Raden's Various Outfits 3-Link Acrylic Key Chain"
新衣装、通常衣装、フラッシュポイント衣装の3種類の3連結アクリルキーホルダーとなっております。
A 3-link acrylic key chain featuring three styles: new outfit, default outfit, and Flashpoint outfit.
イラストは、「こころパズルリズム」の時の、あの後ろにね、可愛いイラスト流れてたんですけれども、
The illustrations are the cute ones shown in the background during "Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm,"
でお馴染み、つばみるく先生でございます！
by none other than Tsubamilk-sensei!
続いてはこちら、デン！
Next up, this one, bam!
「新衣装モチーフピンバッジセット」
"New Outfit Motif Pin Badge Set"
新衣装をモチーフにしたピンバッジセットですよ。
This is a pin badge set based on the motifs of the new outfit.
懐中時計、それから今はしてないけどマスク、シルクハット、モノクルの4種類となっております。
It comes in four types: a pocket watch, a mask (which I'm not wearing right now), a top hat, and a monocle.
続いてはこちら、デン！
Next up, this one, bam!
「ライブ前のトラブル!?ボイス」
"Trouble Before the Live!? Voice"
らでんが書き下ろした台本です。どんなトラブルが...
This is a script written by Raden. What kind of trouble could it be...
るのかは聞いてみてのお楽しみ！
...please listen to it to find out! Enjoy!
そしてフルセット購入特典はこちら、デン！
And here's the full-set purchase bonus, ta-da!
はい、え、儒烏風亭らでん直筆サイン入り、もりくらえん先生描き下ろしポストカード！
Yes! A postcard illustrated by Morikura En-sensei, signed by me, Juufuutei Raden!
今回も購入した方全員に、直筆でサインを書かせていただきますよ！
Once again, I'll be hand-signing them for everyone who purchases the set!
皆さんに届くように精一杯書かせていただくので、よろしくお願いいたします！
I'll do my absolute best to sign them all so they reach you, so please support me!
さらに、特典ボイスもつきます。こちらもらでんが書き下ろしてます！
Plus, it comes with a bonus voice! I wrote the script for this one as well!
はい、ということで...
Yes, so with that...
もう今日ね、もう、すごく、すごい盛りだくさんでございましたが、
We had so many announcements today,
皆さん、追いつけてますか？
are you all keeping up?
結構とんでもないね、発表たくさんしたんですけれども、
I made some pretty mind-blowing announcements today.
らでんが一番、結構とんでもないなと思っております。
Honestly, I'm the one who's most blown away by it all.
ということで、本日の重大発表は、
So, today's major announcements were,
その1：東京国立博物館さんとのコラボ。
First: A collaboration with the Tokyo National Museum.
その2：ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ。
Second: A collaboration with the National Gallery, London.
その3：儒烏風亭らでんがご案内！『ピクセル・ミュージアム』ダウンロードコンテンツ発売決定でございます！
Third: Juufuutei Raden guiding you! The release of the 'Pixel Museum' DLC is officially decided!
情報量がね、多すぎたと思うので、ぜひアーカイブでも確認してみてください！
It was a lot of information, so please check out the archives if you need to!
そして！このあとは、メン限で、アンコールライブあります！
And! After this, there will be an encore live stream exclusive to members!
その時にまた衣装はね、ゆっくりお見せしようかなと思っておりますので、
I'll take some time to show you my outfit in detail then,
えー、まだの方はチャンネル登録と、
so if you haven't yet, please subscribe,
気になるよって方はメンバーでね、またアンコールライブでお会いしましょう！
and if you're interested, join the membership and see you at the encore live!
そしてそして！忘れちゃいけません！このあとすぐ、新曲MV公開でございます！
And, of course! Let's not forget! Right after this, my new song's music video will be released!
頑張って作ったんで、いっぱい見てほしいです！
We worked really hard on it, so I hope you watch it a lot!
はい！
Alright!
ということでございました。
That is all.
え、日頃応援してくださっている皆々様、見ていただいている、聴いていただいているリスナーの皆様のおかげで、
Thanks to all of you who support me daily, and to all the listeners watching and listening,
今回ね、このライブを開催することができました。
we were able to hold this live concert today.
本当に本当にありがとうございました！とっても嬉しいです！
Thank you all so very, very much! I'm so incredibly happy!
これからもね、歌もね、ダンスも、自分のね、やりたいこともいっぱい頑張っていきますので、
From now on, I'll continue to do my best with singing, dancing, and everything else I want to do,
ぜひ応援のほど、よろしくお願いいたします！
so please continue to support me!
それでは！メン限アンコールライブでお会いいたしましょう！
Well then! Let's meet at the member-only encore live stream!
本日の、お相手は、私、儒烏風亭らでんでございました！
Your host for today was me, Juufuutei Raden!
それでは皆様、良い、夜をお過ごしください！
I hope you all have a wonderful night!
さようならでん！
Sayonara-den!